welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
all right let's do some check-ins
um feeling good i feel like
a lot of lightness energy strength
a sense of readiness so welcome to the
stoa i am the steward of the stoa
peter lindbergh and the stowe is a place
for us to cohere and dialogue about what
matters most
at the nice edge of this moment um
today we have uh ria bach
and okay good good good good i have
maybe i have mild dyslexia so i
mispronounced things often so i i and
people with names that you know
i'm not used to saying um and so today
uh ria is going to uh
be engaging in an exercise that she
discovered called collective presence
and just briefly uh theresa may on the
website collective presencing and
emerging human capacity
what becomes possible when we are truly
present together
and if you were here on the last session
uh on wednesday
we had a discussion more like uh more of
a presentation
on it and some questions and q a on it
uh and this practice is all about the
question finding that right question
and so um yeah i don't really know how
it's gonna
be structured uh other than having 90
minutes here together
you can leave any time uh but we are
scheduled for 90 minutes
and so that being said i will hand it
over to uh
riya and then we can begin
okay welcome everybody and thanks for
the invitation peter
um
collective presencing is not is
basically not a practice you can do in
one hour or one and a half hour
so what we will do is something small
a small attempt to actually uh
try if we can get to that place of where
we can all be
really present and where maybe the
conversation and the dialogue
actually can be generative because
that's what we actually do
um
so okay collective processing is
basically
a practice of collective inquiry um
so it's not or it's different
in its purpose than let's say circling
or of
some other respace practices
where being seen and belonging
and the emotional um is very
important or is the ultimate purpose
even in its
subtleties collective prancing
builds on that so it's not that we don't
do that
um but the purpose is to go beyond and
to actually
um
try to be all present to a question that
really matters
and from being present
being able to collectively come to new
insights
and new actions that's basically the
purpose of it
um
i've been writing a whole book about it
after
let's say six or seven years of action
research
i'm not going into all the details
because that would
lead us way too far of course um
and we we will try uh to
applying some of the principles um
to see if we can actually
be in that space be in that space of
what dr scharmer calls this
generative dialogue or what we call the
collective
being collectively present um
so it will be a conversation a dialogue
a circle
practice that actually will go
pretty slow
and how i structured it it's um
we will do a check-in checking around
where everybody can speak
uh answering a question
and after that check-in let's say
everybody has like
almost a minute so that at least after
uh 20-30 minutes we can actually
dive into the dialogue
in the check-in round we will use what
we call a talking piece
as is practice in circle practice
and that's where we build upon
that's where we started when we uh
started this long-term process of
of figuring this out um
so how we do that online is you just say
like i pick up the talking piece and
when you're done
you just name i put it back or
or i'm done or checked in or just make
sure
that you announce when you pick it up
and you announce when you put it down
um
so let's start with a check-in
meaning because we
attach quite some importance to that
everybody
actually every voice can be heard and
even if it's short um i think it would
be nice
to actually hear from each other like
what attracted you to be here now to
spend this
one and a half hours um so we're not
doing the
the checking uh in a way of oh i'm
certain church
and i live there and this is my
profession
of course you can say your name but we i
think we see all names
but importance is that we
try already in the check-in
to enter let's say a layer
deeper or more authentic or more
closer to what really matters to us
and so my invitation is
to answer this like what attracted you
to be
here now short not long stories because
otherwise you don't have
time for um the dialogue itself
but it can be a good dive in already for
what will
come next um so whoever feels like
starting you can just unmute yourself
i guess that you can do that
and um start from there
and silence is also fine if the
we can also slow it down and just
be in the silence which is
okay go ahead
i'll start hi ria um i've done some a
little bit of work with ria in the past
and i used to do a lot of collector
presencing like
practices response practices went away
to do
some heavy emotional lifting and kind of
left presencing a little bit on the
shelf
and i want to reconnect with that
with this inquiry so glad to be here
um i have a little delay on my
senate light internet so i apologize
when i interrupt
um it's not intentional i um
i've been doing some work with with uh
bonnie roy anita roy
and uh she uh pointed me
in this direction and i'm reading your
book
and it just feels um very
home it feels like
uh something either i have known for a
long time
and also something that has um
and uh it's being called not just
because of these political times or
anything else but there's just something
essential about it
that is wanting to spread
thank you thanks
just please follow on whoever feels cold
i am i've been practicing circling for
a few years and
i am also very drawn to the name
collective presenting
i haven't read your book i was at the
talk on wednesday
and yeah the name really called to me
i i've been interested in collective
intelligence
um and collective wisdom for a very long
time
and the recent conversations that have
been popping up around it have been
very stimulating um i've dived really
deep with john verbake's work
and the work the stoa rebel wisdom and a
lot of other
something that's coming up and the virus
pause also seems to be doing something
very distinct
with a synchronization of a collective
awareness
and also a deepening awareness of me
listening to
the stillness that holds me and so i'm
finding practices that
give me a better relationship to my
deeper self
are very attractive to me so that's what
drew me here
hi ria thank you for this offering
i sort of feel like i'm in david's
slipstream from
just the movement of people like david
and
donna and kim and nancy and a few other
people i recognize of
just being feeling pulled forward
to expand the depth
of what we've gathered and garnered
and accumulated from many practices
and looking for also that interaction
where our sort of collective
intuition can move us into
a wholesome enactment
so thank you
i find myself curious about the
correlation between
collective presencing and group flow
state
and i'm wondering if they
are very much yeah like
really like related or intertwined and
um
yeah so i'm just curious about the
relationship between those two and if
collective presence
can bring about group flow state and
yeah how those interact with one another
i attended your talk a day back i think
on on stoa and you'd use two words
which came up in a lot of my personal
inquiries which was generativity and
elegance
and both of them resonated a lot so the
next elegant step was something that
crystallized a lot for me
so i was very curious about it
i came here today because i'm sensing a
really strong
feeling of emotional resonance
collectively among my neighbors and
friends
and some new people i met here and
elsewhere
which is why i'm here as well
hi everyone um
i yeah i'm interested in in
the group think aspect of everything um
but i don't know i just want to share
sort of where my head's at right now
because um
i'm sort of uh trying to hold various
perspectives
of the situation at large um
as far as the relative tranquility of my
immediate surroundings and
you know the potential suffering of
people around the world and
holding that empathy at a
at a distance i
so
it's good to
tap into everyone else's experiences and
awareness and feelings
and um
so hopefully i can integrate
some of the various juxtaposing
minds in my own mind so
um i'm feeling nervous
my heart is beating really fast
and i've never done something like this
before
but i could have done something but i
just
something felt right to be here so i'm
like
proud of myself when i'm here and yeah
this is my first
kind of circling event and i don't know
what it's going to be like but
yeah i'm glad i'm here
i'm glad camille's here i am here
as a student of the campfire it feels
like
and interested in
becoming a deeper listener becoming
more patient and also
uh becoming more skillful as a
communicator
and looking forward to
gathering around physical campfires
physical flames and
yeah looking forward to that and putting
logs on that fire building energy toward
that
also i'm interested in um creating
music songs lyrics about my experiences
around the campfire
and so i feel like i feel very like i'm
like absorb like i'm absorbing knowledge
and information and lessons from you all
and
um really happy to be here
i am here i'm jonathan by the way i'm on
my mom's ipad
i don't know how to change the name um
i'm here because about a month and a
half ago i
mistyped the url someone sent me and
instead of
going to the page that they wanted me to
go to i found the collective presence
book
um and it was very certain this because
it was like
i think very much the book i've been
looking for um especially
um i just came back for some travels and
i had a lot of experiences that i was
having trouble making sense of
and the book helped me make sense of
that um and so i'm
yeah very drawn curious about this
practice and
the energetics of of allowing as it
shows up
in the practice i imagine
jonathan actually introduced me to your
book rhea
and um it seems to tie up so many
different components of life that i'm
exploring i found like rebel wisdom and
then the stoa
and then now you're here so it seems
like different parts of my life
is just coming to one i'm very curious
about the concept and the experience of
emergence
so that's why i'm here
hey i um
yeah i appreciate you hosting this ria
i don't feel like i know much about it
but i i looked over the
chapters of the book um and the
like different section headings and it
seemed very interesting
uh yeah and i'm curious to know how
this might be valuable for
building a group of people an
intentional
group of people or team to
work on something that feels meaningful
and being able to better connect and be
cohesive in that group
that's yeah
my my motivations and inspirations
were sort of triggered by james there or
ra it reminded me of why i'm here i
sort of am curious about the building of
intentional groups and
and of bringing uh collective presence
into groups i'm already a part
of and being able to introduce
elements of that to relationships that i
have so that
they can be a little more a little more
emergent
presence aware those kind of things
hello everyone wonderful to be with you
all
and thank you ria i'm here my i think my
heart just drew me here
through ver coming from various we space
practices
and really with a deep interest in how
to really
move more in my day-to-day life from
emergence
um first of all i will apologize
for it because you cannot see my face i
will arrange that better the next time
my motivation for being here is
also exploration and curiosity
so it's like i've come here for from
recommendation
and i see it as an
orientation into
this concept in your book thank you
uh hello everyone um
the reason i'm here is uh well basically
curiosity and trust
because wherever i go if something
piques my interest
i seem to get something from it even
though if i don't know exactly what it's
going to be
and if it's done by people i trust
it's a very highly likelihood that it's
going to be something of value
even if it's a reiteration of something
that i've heard somewhere it's
kind of strengthening that sense of of
knowing so that's why i'm here
thank you
hi everyone i'm brandon i'm also feeling
quite a bit anxious and nervous so thank
you camille for opening the door to
sharing that i appreciate that
it's also nice to see a few familiar
faces as well
i have been involved in quite a bit of
insight dialogue practice
and in that work i've been interested in
how every pairing
every partnership that i've been in in
that practice has brought up something
novel
every time and it feels totally
different every time
so i'm i'm curious in seeing how
adding more people and um and how the
different combinations and permutations
of people how
changing little elements might bring up
something new
there's a couple of people left
um yeah i'm also
i find my heart beats really fast when i
encounter these situations
i'm feeling really feeling the
opportunity
right now and how our normal has been
disrupted
there's this really rich fertile
learning space potential
i can feel it i felt really
affected rio when you said um we need to
fall in love with potential
um so i'm like yeah i feel like oh like
i'm in this
new love relationship or something cause
it's making my heart beat fast
um yeah the sense of there being kind of
a lot at stake and
and and then like how to just how do we
hold all those energies
and feel each other and breathe together
in
in this new space um so that we can
create a context where
we can make the most of this learning
ground
that we're in yeah
that's it
i'm donna and i
spend quite a bit of time in collective
presencing and
different types of we space i read your
book and resonate
deeply with it thank you
i'm attracted to the adventurousness
and the unpredictability of the
collective
and what's really present with me today
is a lot of uncertainty
and i'm looking forward
and open to being in that uncertainty
with everyone
yeah hi um i'm also quite
curious about how a practice of of
presence works uh works online
i've also done inside dialogue uh but
uh never through the medium so
it's it's it's quite interesting to see
that
something carries over just just by
working with the introduction
so i look forward to it thanks
hello um so i've also been involved with
a lot of these collective insight
practices i guess you can say
uh also with with bonnie these past few
weeks and
i i've been draining or i'm swamped
in insights and i'm feeling overwhelmed
at this point
uh and so next week i'm just not doing
like any zoom calls at this point
and just taking time off uh to integrate
you know all these aha moments into into
my being if that makes sense
uh and
yeah i'm here because i don't know it
feels it feels right to be here
i don't know there's there's something
about uh
the energy at the soa always and then in
these bigger spaces
that uh that attracts me that i that i
like and
uh that's why i'm here
okay i think we caught everyone i didn't
make notes but i'll okay so
uh i wasn't i came late and i didn't
know exactly what we're doing so it was
scared to say anything
the question was what attracted you to
be here and just
yeah i'm also scared of my answer too
because it's like in some ways it was
just like
i saw your name and i was like this is
someone who i know is doing good work
curious what it was about and i didn't
think that was enough um
but i think additional context is i've
been floating in the game v space
and i've seen your name pop up a whole
bunch of times
and i think just from hearing
everybody's
shares it's like oh yes all these exact
words that i'm
playing around with these days are all
collective
around uncertainty around emergence that
and i'm just
like excited to just get a taste of what
what you're trying to do and see if this
makes sense for me to dive a little bit
deeper
um because i think like
i think the way to move into the future
is not individuality is more about the
collective
and trying to play with that
i can go so why am i here
i don't know why i'm here but i
quite enjoying being here and not
knowing why
and the question that's bubbling up
right now is
what is the best question to figure out
why
we are here
thanks big i think we all checked in
and actually that question
that peter raises um
as he said in the beginning finding a
question that can
guide a conversation or a dialogue
is really an art in itself and
in our quick planning last week
peter and i said we would we would do
some prep on
on wednesday which didn't happen
so i went with what
with that and i've posted
the question that we will use as a
guideline
for our dialogue in the chat
and the question is taking into account
the times we are in this kind of
bunch of people that we are here um
what has your attention mainly and
maybe if possible what could be a
challenging question that we could
maybe work with in the future um
there might be a possibility if there's
uh
energy and appetite that we do a series
of four or five
like four or five weeks in a row with
the same group
um so we will see at the end um
but before we go into the dialogue um
we already have used this talking piece
thing uh and it's actually on zoom it's
actually
you all have good um practice of
muting yourself so it's also visible
who wants to keep quiet and who wants to
speak
but as we move into a dialogue
i invite people also to speak from that
place
where you might not have
preformed ideas about already
yeah i invite you to speak from a place
that
might come up just right here and right
now
and even the people who already um
posted the question in the chat maybe
even
go deeper or wider or below or i don't
know
but what is it um that you could
actually bring from a space
um
what we then try to do in collective
frenzy
is also to invite
inner knowing intuition and not just
the thoughts we already had not
these preformed conceptual spaces
not delete them
or ignore them but having
a wisdom maybe or a space
of inquiry where everything
can be present every kind of knowing can
be present
and so it means that if you
uh unmute yourself it might be that
you don't have words the first 10
seconds
and that's fine yeah and or there's some
silence between your
sentences and that's fine we will know
when you speak like okay this is undone
or you mute yourself then we see that
you're done speaking
so a way of
tuning into that is what we call you
speak
into the middle and you speak from the
middle like
imagine that we are really sitting in a
circle
there is a middle somewhere it's not
like oh i agree with what you said
it's not that kind of conversation
it's an inquiry into what is what is
something that we might see together
or we might see that some of the
questions we are holding
go in a similar direction and maybe not
we will see um
the other side is also don't
censor yourself too much um
maybe you tell a story that happened
this morning
or something that reminds you of
but try to sense like where does it come
from does it come from your inner
silence from your inner knowing
or it's just so oh i want to tell a
story yeah
because i want to be heard or something
so just
checking yourself if you if you can
distinguish
at all but just try to play with them
yeah
and so it's also an invitation for all
of us
to actually listening to the whole
of what is going on and not just
the contents but also
if if we would sit in a circle could you
expand
your attention to include like everyone
so it's not you're not talking to me
only we're talking to each other and
you could expand your awareness
to hold like the whole circle
um if that is possible at
all um but we will also
work with okay somebody
bring something up a story
a question try to
let it sink in first before there's
something that comes up in you
so that we might build on each other
and sometimes it's totally different
and we take it seems like we take a
totally different path
and that's fine too we don't need to
have
a solution at the end or an agreement
or anything um
and silence is welcome maybe
at some point nobody wants to speak
that's
also fine yeah
and as a last
i think maybe
can we challenge maybe here and there
some of the collective assumptions we
are holding
like that's i think it's crucial for us
to move into the new
whatever is coming whatever is going on
already
um
what are assumptions that that hold us
in the
in in the box that's too small and
we might touch upon some of being able
to name some but we can go beyond
um
and there was one question somebody
asked like what has collect friends to
do with
flow state i said it's
flow state but in the conversation
in in how you talk with each other
you could come to a flow state i'm not
saying we will get that
today i don't know um
but it's
it's a different kind of energy first of
all to kind of
really listening deeply inside
and deeply to each other and to the
whole of the group that we are
for today
with that i think i
i placed the virtual talking piece
in the middle of the circle and i will
read out the question
once more um so that
um so taking into account the times we
are in
and this sponge of people
what is it that has your attention
at the moment and if there is a question
what could be a challenging question
for all of us to dive deeper into
so that's the invitation and we will
see where we go and
i understand that some people are
anxious if you have never
done this but you're free to talk you're
free to listen
but if you feel like
there seems to be something bubbling up
feel free
to unmute yourself and start and so we
can
we can start in silence and and let the
process go
uh you unmute yourself and we mute
yourself and
we will see where we end up so by um
10 to the hour we need to stop
i i will close the dialogue and have
a short check out
so it's up to all of us
um if i may
what i'm noticing right now is a
reiteration
of a theme that i've actually had in a
previous
call as well is this kind of being
between the rock and the hard place of
both wanting to connect
deeply and at the same time being
overwhelmed
by kind of a multitude of streams and
the
complexity of the language and and
topics
and that immediately kind of shows me
that
that same as in in the question that i
raised
being still maintaining my awareness
when there's so much going on around
and that draws my attention then to
everybody else
because i don't really know if anybody
else is experiencing the same thing as i
do
and and i know that nobody actually
sees if i do have that experience when
i'm
already lost and i'm not no longer
following what somebody's saying
and this causes me to fear that
i might be missing something of value
and it kind of
that the time will pass and yet
some things kind of fall between the
chairs
and uh there's no
there's no toolage for for communication
about this
low capacity to take information and
maybe
a requirement for a repetition or
summarizing and everything it seems like
kind of ad hoc
or just kind of building everything up
in a moment
and chips falling in various
directions thank you
thank you
[Music]
i feel called the premiere
uh i don't know really what to say and i
think that's what your invitation was
for
generally someone who plans what they
say before you know
saying anything so this is just fun for
me i'm trying to practice this
um i think
um right before this call um
someone like right before entering this
call someone said something profound to
me
and i think i'll share the story um
right i think yesterday
someone essentially told me that
phil i am okay with
her knowing that you will be hurt
by this action and not do anything about
it
and so i just got on this call asking a
coach like
is this ethical like she is willing to
hurt me
um and like should i have this person in
my life
and he essentially said that one of the
most important
lessons you could learn in life
is that i write down um
the experience of pain and hurt
is um
not distinct is distinct from right and
wrong
and i think it's it's taken me out to
this like
thing from a group of people here that i
know
called lsa or upstart uh collaboratory
which
is thinking about like what if the world
doesn't have any like right or wrong
um it's more like phil this is a
learning experience for
you and i think that's
one of the questions that's on my mind
right now
[Music]
pick up the piece
um i noticed my mind is around
um an openness as i am with the people
there's a
sense of um
my heart opens and softens and flutters
a bit as i
consider us um
and i and i also feel that there's
something
more possible something that i'm not
looking at
that invites an even greater opening
there my um
i would say my deepest compass is like
wonder
that's where at the deepest part of me
that the part that
brings forward what i pay attention to
and it and it seems to interact
interestingly with a sense of
curiosity and doubt
i am i'm suspicious of any time that i'm
certain
100 sure of something
my wonder protests or my curiosity
protests
and i and i look more deeply
i'm what am i missing
what's what am i not seeing
um and
for the people who are here and the
deeper question that may be challenging
is
who is not here
there are a number of people that i
don't see almost ever represented
in these particular calls
and there's a deep
wondering about what is that
i don't have a conclusion about the
rightness or wrongness of it
but it's persistent it's a it's
that silence of a component of humanity
that's not
being felt not feeling the call to
participate
is becoming louder um
and it has me wonder what
um what am i not listening to
there is there an invitation that i'm
not making
because they're not invitation i'm not
feeling in myself to listen
to more deeply
and i feel a little frightened of
what i might find if i if i open myself
fully to that question
and put the piece back
um have a few words oh go for it let's
do this
okay thanks um yeah that's
i just want to respond to david i
i'm getting intense imagery of the
campfire and all of us
sitting there with the light that we're
trying to
kindle but
yeah the presence of this darkness
behind our backs
is definitely extremely strong
and from these circling experiences that
i've had
i'm very minimal but
you know the analogy of the fire being
something that
you know is the warmth that brings us
together
i i'm also very wary of of
of that darkness and the depth and the
danger
and the potential being greater in the
darkness
but how how do you look at that in the
right way how does that
how is that incorporated there's
something about
always bringing to light the assumptions
and always having
some kind of
renewal or a
cycle of of birth and death that that
that you know some building something up
breaking it down
um i'm reminded of something from
verveiki's lectures of
the the uh
the sand that is dripped on creates a
peak
at but that only but but it collapses at
some
carrying capacity but that that fosters
the you know a larger diameter for the
new peaks so
but how you know
anyway that's out there now
i was interested in um
some of what phil said
and the like what if there is no
right and wrong um
and i yeah i wonder about what other
ways there are to think about
things that aren't using the right and
wrong
framework which feels to me like it
appeals to
some sort of authority um
and one of the the thing one of the ones
that comes to my mind
is uh like what what is the impact of
any particular action and what impact
do we want to have um
yeah and i guess i i feel curious about
uh like exploring other ways of thinking
about that or
or or different ways of of measuring
that
yeah for me there's an imagery of
moving past to a tunnel instead of
coming out at the other end
and there's a question of
choosing to build
something but it's not entirely clear
what something needs to emerge something
needs to be birthed
and i feel like there is a creative
energy that
wishes to be in service of building
something but it's not clear
which way it's it
it sort of moves to
i'm feeling a connection between that
question
about impact
and what david shared about
and um yoshio2 described it as the
darkness
uh behind us at the campfire
um and all the people that aren't in the
room
and wondering how we can
sense what's happening what impacts are
happening if they're not in the room
i am loved this
and so i'm sitting up
at a produced monastery and spend a lot
of time looking at trees in nature
now like almost extending this to not
just like
who's not in the room as in people but
then also like
all the like the living things that are
there
and like how can we listen into those
and really like
hear what the earth is trying to tell us
yeah i feel that brings up
the sense somehow
you unleash the sense i have of this
sort of swirling
energy right here with this group
and it feels like it has lots of ears
and eyes
it just uh
is coalescing within but looking
without at the same time like there's
a response to those questions that
everyone
has had and it seems really alive
now i want to follow up on that
as i was trying to write about all this
in the book
and i don't have any religious language
that
is meaningful for myself i i noticed
basically my how you say my
my guidance or where i try to sense
is where do i feel
that of something that is alive
and so that is way different than is it
right or wrong um of course
when you measure something that can be
right or wrong
or something but
in in life in general
and i would say especially in these
times
where so much so-called certainties fall
away
um what is
the project what are the people what are
the questions that
bring me alive that that
is is what guides me and that's what i
want to
try to bring into a conversation and
into a dialogue like
when we feel that
this conversation is alive
and can we can we speak
can we articulate that what is
really alive in us and not only what we
think
but that what is like yeah
it's really
and
i somehow an assumption
a belief yeah
if we have the capacities and
intelligence and the experience and
blah blah to
figure something out around this
we might be the ones who can teach
others
and not everyone needs to be the
teachers or
the initiators of this kind of
a live conversations
and um um
then we just witness so because there's
also
most of the time all of the times it's a
lot of
pain that we carry ourselves even if we
might be
all the privileged people um
if you're able to be with them
we might be able to spread it or that's
one of the beliefs
so what's coming up is um
asking the right question is like
making love in the most spiritual way
possible
and i have a strong desire to start
making love
i noticed that
i've come alive or experienced this
aliveness when
um people are speaking and sharing
metaphors
as well as sharing their
very personal experience so like them
when the metaphor of the darkness behind
us was spoken of like i
is there's an imagery like a sensation
of like being there
and this aliveness that i experienced um
like i came into contact with the
feeling of the wilderness
and then when phil's speaking about some
of his personal experiences feeling this
like
tender um heart connection and then
and then for me is like these moments
with
the the metaphor and the feeling that's
where i felt most like i was making love
and so it's um yeah noticing those
sensations inside of me and like
orienting myself toward that
is is juicy
my heart is kind of pounding now
which i think means i'm supposed to say
something
in these exercises i think it's
important i try not to think of what i'm
going to say i think that's the purpose
and it
occurred to me that from what people
have been saying about right and wrong
in the darkness and
uh what i said earlier to there's like
some mystery out there
that we are all experiencing together
and i noticed unlike normal times
we're sharing with each other
um this morning i
i had a long list of things to do as
usual i said no i'm just something
that's important and i
tried to write my wife a poem
and i finished it of course naturally i
thought it was good
and then i reread it and i realized that
i had pivoted from
trying to appreciate her love her
to use the word you know make love to
her through words
um i pivoted back to myself
and what i was doing in reality was
nonetheless i was articulating to use a
word that someone else just used i was
articulating what is real
which is again i think what we're all
trying to do at this time is
tell it like it is
what has my attention is
the life of the lovemaking that we're
all engaged in
and how and the impact of each person's
input outpouring
directs the collective lovemaking
life
um what's uh what also has my attention
is
how all the rectangles on the screen
appear to be like beating hearts
and there's a drawing
into
each heart and then a central heart
an image that keeps coming up for me
is not only is each square a beating
heart which
which feels right to me donna um but
also
a cog and a system of gears that are all
connected
and whenever someone rises up to share
then that cog
moves a couple of a couple of clicks
and then i could see the nearest cogs
clicking
along and then the furthest cogs finally
also clicking in place
um yeah it's beautiful
uh what just arose in me is kind of a
tiny bit of annoyance
with this realization that we're so kind
of
calm and peaceful and connected
and kind of come by yeah and everything
is nice
but the world is not so and kind of i
feel this urge to disrupt this and just
kind of give a bit of a challenge and to
say hey
come on and
[Music]
just see where that goes because yeah
it's
we're already in some kind of bubble in
a way we're all
more aligned it's easy for us i think to
eventually
talk and get an agreement of some sorts
even if we would have very different
views on particular issues we would
still be able to respect each other and
talk
but we're a total minority of the world
and and i just don't trust
this kind of setup kind of
scaling up so easily i think it's just
the easy part right now it's important
to have the easy part but it's not
always easy and
well i don't trust this
sense it's it's just like it's too easy
sometimes i want to challenge
thank you
yeah imagine that we would run
the same project all of us and we
try to be in this dialogue but
that would be way more at stake
for each of us so then it becomes more
difficult
and there becomes assumptions um
uh what you said to hurt me and blah
blah
but it's also hard
to come back to this space
where you could actually have new
insights
eventually but you're totally right
and into what's could have been some
part of my
check-in or my framing in the beginning
but
you have faces in this and for us it's
it's it's a very unnatural setting
like i might most of you never see you
again we will never be a group
but if it would be like a project team
then there's way more at stake and then
you go to
phases and cycles and you're totally
right
but we can at least exercise a bit
even when it's easy for whenever it
becomes more difficult
that's my technique
i was considering like how would we as a
collective
uncover the where we have the most
agency
to
direct the most positive impact or the
most meaningful change
and that and and that i was
almost resisting or hesitant because i
was like well
would i why am i forcing something that
like i need to find a place where i can
do something
this energy in me and i was kind of
feeling both those sides
and but there is this um sense where
like yesterday i for no real
meaningful goal i kind of like scaled
the side of a sketchy cliff
where there were like rocks kind of like
sliding down and it was really loose
and i did it for the experience of like
being on the edge of it
and because i felt safe enough but i was
challenged my movement skills were
challenged
and so there is this sense of me that
kind of craves
for the the stakes to be raised if you
will
um and then i'm curious like how to
choose that when when am i forcing it
when is it dangerous when is it
um and yes i appreciate this
question this energy this challenge and
then i'm wondering sort of like well
now now what where do i go where do i
aim
wanna pick up the stick
okay
um
i'm um not sure what's
what's exactly there but i'm uh
there's something that's just been
hanging
and it has to do with the notions of of
groups themselves like
one is that they're sort of an
assumption
that we develop
within groups and maybe that's just true
maybe that's just what humans do is we
gather into collectives of some type
and make something happen out of that
and that feels both um
kind of exciting on one side and the
other side of it is
oh there's something like something
else that wants to come forth like
there's more
there's more possibilities than this
continuing just to gather into groups
and develop and especially develop
ourselves wholly
as this amazing community that can do
all kinds of things there's something
um it feels missing
or just not meeting a
potential and i think there's also a
little fear within
me perhaps of past experiences of groups
and just not being
you know the polarity between the group
and myself
i think there's that's in there but i it
just
um because the final thing that wants to
be
said is is
is this an assumption that
our collective action and our collective
intelligence and wisdom and what however
we want to say it
insight comes always through groups
um and is there another way of spreading
whatever this love may be
i think that's enough on the piece back
wow that's an awesome question kim i'm a
group
i'm a group uh uh
probably junkie so to hear the question
of whether or not
there's some something that's not and
it's the
it's the the me and the we it's both but
you hear that there's something else
which is exciting
um i really appreciated
roland that's you bringing up the um
what we're not noticing here what we
what what maybe at the back of the
campfire
and underscoring um
that you did ria that
that um what we have at stake
and i realized that i often don't bring
what i have at stake
to groups which is my life you know i
really do have a lot at stake here
because this is my one and only life and
my one and only time
so really appreciating you know the
naming of that you gave
that this is important for each one of
us in a very personal way
it's not a posturing that we're you know
that we're often called to do in the
regular world
so just just appreciating that
i think what's coming up for me is like
um
there's like a slight like
unrest internally and
i'm kind of curious what it is and then
there's like a lot of part of me that's
like attaching stories to it
um which is out of like pure compare
contrast there's like this like
like i want to get somewhere and like i
want to come to conclusions or
kind of what tyson was saying maybe like
um
like wanting some sort of direction
or like
like this like energy efficiency and
like
optimization side comes in and like that
like it feels just like so fluid and
flowing i'm like
let's get somewhere and um and then
there's also this part that's like oh
well like maybe this is like
what you're being triggered with right
now of staying with
the process and the not knowing and the
discomfort
um and giving that space
yeah what i wanna speak to is um
as westerns we're so
trained to know to know the answers to
know
the next thing to know the plan to know
the goals
um and if we don't know
it it becomes an emotional tension like
i need a solution i need we need an
action we need a decision
yeah and
in these times in the world
i think we are also invited to
be able to hold a lot of intensity
and intensity can be the pain
or the ugliness of what's going on or
the war
or trauma or
or insecurity or not knowing
there's all different ways of intensity
and to me it seems that
where we are in the world is really
inviting
us to can we stay centered
and grounded
not on our own but sometimes we need
each other
to be able to do that because
the ugliness the uncertainty is so big
and we can hardly hold it on our own
and i guess some people
mentioned the wonder and the mystery
and i think if we can hold intensity
it's easier i think to hold
mystery and wonderment
or one ring i don't know what's the
right thing
that's an assumption
i'm i'm feeling like
you're speaking to a question maria
what is the significance of what we're
doing right now
um i really when abby was speaking
i felt um like i was watching her
do the thing that
bonnie bonita roy was talking about
um like tracking what she's
the activity of her mind what she's
sensing
um what's she's choosing where she's
choosing to put her attention
and and um it sort of feels like we're
in this
group meditation interactive meditation
together
uh practicing like all being on the side
of the cliff together
like what tyson was talking about you
know but
it's just a little cliff so we know
we're okay we're not gonna
destroy anything together um no one's
gonna fall
um and hurt themselves but yeah
i'm feeling
the power of this
i'm uh i'm having the sensation of
everybody
on the screen being like the
little thoughts in my own mind when i'm
trying to
control my you know just in preparation
for meditation
a little little chatter it's sort of
represented now
everybody just you know riffing off each
each other and um
sort of just that's my experience
right now oh yeah
i noticed tanya when you said that um
it's just a small cliff
we can't really hurt ourselves i jumped
i'm not so sure
i don't know how deep it is um my sense
is
i don't know where the bottom is it
might
not there might not be a bottom
um and there's some
there's a desire in me to i have a
desire to move fast the the
feeling of grasping that ria mentioned
and when i don't know
is there i can feel that it's an
aliveness in me
um and
the shallowness of the
grasp that i feel as a collective we can
dig
into this doesn't satisfy the depth that
i want to go
so there's a there's a tension just
there how do i let go
of my expectations
and my assumptions enough to
get to the depth of having a sense of
what the shape of this thing is
ah yeah
i'm having thoughts right now about um
the idea of certainty came up uh
is coming up and
of knowing and thinking that we must
know and i'm seeing
the uh or i'm thinking about the
pandemic situation as
almost like a reminder that the idea of
being able to know
at all is just an idea sort of like an
illusion
and maybe yeah i'm appreciating the
pandemic right now for it's
bringing that real reminder of the
wildness
of existence
what's coming up is maybe the right
question
makes love with the unknown
i'm thinking right now about a question
that can be
held and not even not needing to be
answered
yeah well
that was already quite a rich exchange
here
um as we coming close
to the end and sorry i haven't
followed the chat because that was too
much to do
what was growing in me during the call
is um as i was playing with this idea of
um offering like
four or five weeks in a row for the
same group like if people would then
agree to to be uh present
in the four or the five sessions
and i was wondering if
any one of you
would be interested in attending
that would be nice if you could write in
the chat
if you're interested in attending
and if there would be one two or three
people who would be interested
in figuring out what would be the
guiding question
for that series that would be
a really lovely thing to do um
so you can use the chat to do that
to put your name up or your emails or
whatever
um i'm not going to read it right now um
so please make sure we have the chat
repeater
it doesn't disappear um we can do it
another way too
um people can just email me uh and then
i can forward those emails to you
that might be interested uh and i also
like to say uh
offer the invitation again that if you'd
like to come to the stoa on a weekly
basis
and do whatever you'd like to do because
this is magic here i i think we're all
would welcome you with open arms and the
gift economy um i mentioned i can put
you on the gift economy website too
so if people want to give a gift to you
directly for your gift
then we can do that as well okay
um and as closing as a checkout round um
maybe it's nice to hear from everybody
like
how are you leaving um we don't have one
minute for each person but like
two three words or one sentence or
how are you leaving this chord
how are you feeling what do you think
with you just
half sentence a few words that just nice
to close and that we know from each
other a tiny bit
i feel like a richer soup with
more and more spice and flavor
i feel like i'm dangling with delicious
anticipation
i feel the light in the dark are are um
there's room for both
like we're in a big petri dish and
who knows what's going to pop out of it
i'm excited about being on the cliff
with everybody no fear
deepening my relationship with wonder
and
the question of what if
i feel there's been some movement of
energy
um i'm not sure how i mean the words
transmit energy and and information but
besides the words
and besides even the emotional level
there's been some kind of an energy
movement
still uncertainty
i'm sensing like i'm walking around in a
kind of
fog and at the same time although i'm a
bit
desperate and sad about it at the same
time it's
kind of a warm fog and it's abrasive
i am scared to jump but planning to jump
magical melting pot
i love being challenged some good
challenges from people
i feel like moving through my
resistances
moving my body physically
yeah i'm feeling very viscerally
activated
i feel like i've sprouted some curious
and creeping tendrils
looking wandering blindly to grasp at
something
and i leave an advanced
and exciting
i originally wanted to say that uh i
feel delicious
but then just listening to each person
my state changed and what i wanted to
say
changed and what i'm experiencing right
now is just a desire to ask a question
which is delicious
feeling expanded
uh overwhelming sort of
sense of a large subtle body
i'm feeling like whatever that sensation
is after you
write in your journal
i'm feeling like a combination of
like frustration and sweetness
i'm feeling lighter
ready and excited
i don't know if there's somebody else
who wants to speak
before we move out and
if not then we can all unread
and say bye and
queen nice for whatever language
who was that